Guide to the Basil Lee Whitener Papers, 1889-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Trips Series, 1944-1968,primarily 1959-1968
  - Vietnam Trip, 1966
    Whitener took an inspection trip to South-Vietnam and Southeast Asia, July, 1966. Stops were scheduled in Hawaii, the Philippine Islands, Thailand, and Taiwan. Included is much background material for the trip, such as fact sheets concerning Vietnamese commercial imports, economic assistance, and people. The Agency for International Development produced other briefing material on such topics as education, public safety, refugees, and agriculture. In addition, there is mimeographed information from the Library of Congress Legislative Reference Service on the Vietnamese War, the Soviet Union, and the Korean Conflict. Included are itineraries, maps, instructions, sightseeing information, and pamphlets concerning locations Whitener visited. There are some personal notes that he made while on the trip, as well as a copy of remarks he made in the House of Representatives on July 13, 1966, upon his return.
    - Papers, 1965, May-1966, June (Box 200, Folder 6-7)
    - Papers, 1966, July-Dec.and undated (Box 201, Folder 1-6)
  - Vietnam Trip, 1967
    Whitener and Congressmen Charles E. Wiggins and James C. Corman, all went on this trip in their capacities as members of the House Committee on the Judiciary. The trip was from March 25 to April 2, 1967. Included in the folders are correspondence; material relating to the Uniform Code of Military Justice for Vietnam; as well as Whitener's personal notes, memoranda, and recommendations
    - Papers, 1967, Jan.-1968, Feb.and undated (Box 202, Folder 1-5)
    - Pictures,1967and undated (Box 202, Folder 6)
- Post Office Series, 1944-1968,primarily 1950-1968
  The contents concern matters relating to local post offices in Whitener's district, such as the location, construction, and dedication of new post office buildings; renting of post office quarters; improving and enlarging postal facilities; and the closing of postal stations. Other issues discussed include personnel matters, such as filling job vacancies and requests for transfers; changes and extensions of routes; a postal pay increase bill; the Civil Service retirement law; and requests for investigations of problems at post offices. The majority of the material, which consists of correspondence, printed material, and forms, is arranged by county and then subdivided by towns. The files before Whitener took office in January, 1957, are those of Woodrow Wilson Jones, Whitener's predecessor in office.
  - General Material:
    - City, rural, and lock boxes, 1960-1967 (Box 203, Folder 1)
    - General, 1944-1968and undated (Box 203, Folder 2-5)
  - Counties:
    - Alexander County
      - Taylorsville, 1966-1968 (Box 203, Folder 6)
    - Avery County
      - Banner Elk, 1962-1969 (Box 203, Folder 7)
      - Crossnore, 1962-1968 (Box 203, Folder 8)
      - Elk Park, 1963-1964 (Box 203, Folder 9)
      - Linville, 1963-1967 (Box 203, Folder 10)
      - Montezuma, 1963 (Box 203, Folder 11)
      - Newland, 1962-1966 (Box 204, Folder 1)
      - Pineola, 1963 (Box 204, Folder 2)
      - Plumtree, 1963-1965 (Box 204, Folder 3)
    - Burke County
      - Connellys Springs, 1964-1966 (Box 204, Folder 4)
      - Drexel, 1964-1966 (Box 204, Folder 5)
      - Glen Alpine, 1967 (Box 204, Folder 6)
      - Hildebran, 1964-1968 (Box 204, Folder 7)
      - Icard, 1966-1968 (Box 204, Folder 8)
      - Jonas Ridge, 1966-1968 (Box 204, Folder 9)
      - Morganton, 1963-1968 (Box 204, Folder 10)
      - Rhodhiss, 1966 (Box 204, Folder 11)
      - Rutherford College, 1966-1968 (Box 204, Folder 12)
      - Valdese, 1962-1966 (Box 204, Folder 13)
    - Caldwell County, 1967-1968 (Box 205, Folder 1)
    - Catawba County
      - Claremont, 1962-1968 (Box 205, Folder 2)
      - Conover, 1962-1968 (Box 205, Folder 3)
      - Catawba, 1963-1968 (Box 205, Folder 4)
      - Hickory, 1962-1967and undated (Box 205, Folder 5-7)
      - Longisland, 1964 (Box 206, Folder 1)
      - Maiden, 1962 (Box 206, Folder 2)
      - Newton, 1963-1965 (Box 206, Folder 3)
      - Sherrills Ford, 1964-1968 (Box 206, Folder 4)
      - Terrell, 1964 (Box 206, Folder 5)
    - Cleveland County
      - Belwood, 1951-1954 (Box 206, Folder 6)
      - Boiling Springs, 1961-1965 (Box 206, Folder 7)
      - Casar, 1950-1963 (Box 206, Folder 8)
      - Earl, 1952-1953, 1966-1968 (Box 206, Folder 9)
      - Fallston, 1951, 1959-1961 (Box 206, Folder 10)
      - Grover, 1954-1967 (Box 206, Folder 11)
      - Kings Mountain, 1952-1967 (Box 206, Folder 12)
      - Lattimore, 1952-1963 (Box 207, Folder 1)
      - Lawndale, 1951-1965 (Box 207, Folder 2)
      - Mooresboro, 1952-1965 (Box 207, Folder 3-4)
      - Patterson Springs, 1958-1959 (Box 207, Folder 5)
      - Polkville, 1958-1966 (Box 207, Folder 6)
      - Shelby, 1951-1961 (Box 207, Folder 7-8)
      - Shelby, 1962-1968 (Box 208, Folder 1-2)
      - Waco, 1951-1952 (Box 208, Folder 3)
    - Gaston County
      - Alexis, 1955, 1966-1968 (Box 208, Folder 4)
      - Belmont, 1951-1968and undated (Box 208, Folder 5-6)
      - Bessemer City, 1953-1966and undated (Box 208, Folder 7)
      - Cherryville, 1951-1963and undated (Box 209, Folder 1-2)
      - Cramerton, 1960, 1965-1968 (Box 209, Folder 3)
      - Dallas, 1951-1966and undated (Box 209, Folder 4-5)
      - Gastonia, 1951-1963 (Box 209, Folder 6-7)
      - Gastonia, 1964-1968and undated (Box 210, Folder 1)
      - High Shoals, 1959, 1965-1968 (Box 210, Folder 2)
      - Lowell, 1955-1968 (Box 210, Folder 3)
      - McAdenville, 1959-1965 (Box 210, Folder 4)
      - Mount Holly, 1951-1965and undated (Box 210, Folder 5)
      - Stanley, 1950-1967and undated (Box 210, Folder 6)
    - Iredell County
      - Barium Springs, 1967-1968 (Box 210, Folder 7)
      - Mooresville, 1966-1968 (Box 210, Folder 8)
      - Statesville, 1966-1968 (Box 210, Folder 9)
      - Troutmans, 1967 (Box 210, Folder 10)
      - Turnersburg, 1968 (Box 210, Folder 11)
      - Union Grove, 1966-1968 (Box 210, Folder 12)
    - McDowell County
      - Ashford, 1954 (Box 211, Folder 1)
      - Glenwood, 1951-1953 (Box 211, Folder 2)
      - Little Switzerland, 1961 (Box 211, Folder 3)
      - Marion, 1951-1962and undated (Box 211, Folder 4-6)
      - Nebo, 1955 (Box 211, Folder 7)
      - North Cove, 1952-1954 (Box 211, Folder 8)
      - Old Fort, 1952-1957 (Box 211, Folder 9)
    - Madison County
      - Barnard, 1954 (Box 211, Folder 10)
      - Big Pine, 1951 (Box 211, Folder 11)
      - Bluff, 1952-1953 (Box 211, Folder 12)
      - English, 1952 (Box 211, Folder 13)
      - Hot Springs, 1951-1962and undated (Box 211, Folder 14)
      - Ivey, 1951 (Box 211, Folder 15)
      - Joe, 1950-1952 (Box 211, Folder 16)
      - Luck, 1952 (Box 211, Folder 17)
      - Mars Hill, 1950-1959 (Box 212, Folder 1)
      - Marshall, 1952-1962and undated (Box 212, Folder 2-4)
      - Paint Rock, 1954-1962 (Box 212, Folder 5)
      - Spring Creek, 1955 (Box 212, Folder 6)
      - Trust, 1952 (Box 212, Folder 7)
      - Walnut, undated (Box 212, Folder 8)
      - Worley, 1951 (Box 212, Folder 9)
    - Mitchell County
      - Bakersville, 1962-1965 (Box 212, Folder 10)
      - Penland, 1963 (Box 212, Folder 11)
      - Spruce Pine, 1964-1966 (Box 212, Folder 12)
    - Polk County
      - Columbus, 1951-1962 (Box 213, Folder 1-2)
      - Lynn, 1951, 1957 (Box 213, Folder 3)
      - Melvin Hill, 1955 (Box 213, Folder 4)
      - Mill Spring, 1951-1962 (Box 213, Folder 5)
      - Saluda, 1951-1952, 1961 (Box 213, Folder 6)
      - Tryon, 1953-1961 (Box 213, Folder 7)
    - Rutherford County
      - Alexander Mills, 1951, 1955 (Box 213, Folder 8)
      - Avondale, 1962-1965 (Box 213, Folder 9)
      - Bostic, 1960-1963 (Box 213, Folder 10)
      - Caroleen, 1953, 1962-1963 (Box 213, Folder 11)
      - Chimney Rock, 1951-1957, 1965 (Box 213, Folder 12)
      - Cliffside, 1952-1964 (Box 213, Folder 13)
      - Ellenboro, 1955-1965 (Box 214, Folder 1)
      - Forest City, 1951-1965and undated (Box 214, Folder 2-3)
      - Gilkey, 1958 (Box 214, Folder 4)
      - Harris, 1951-1966 (Box 214, Folder 5)
      - Henrietta, 1951-1965 (Box 214, Folder 6)
      - Hollis, 1953 (Box 214, Folder 7)
      - Lake Lure, 1952-1965and undated (Box 214, Folder 8)
      - Ruth, 1956-1958 (Box 215, Folder 1)
      - Rutherfordton, 1950-1966 (Box 215, Folder 2-3)
      - Spindale, 1950-1967 (Box 215, Folder 4)
      - Union Mills, 1951-1953 (Box 215, Folder 5)
    - Wautauga County, 1968 (Box 215, Folder 6)
    - Yancey County
      - Bald Creek, 1952-1961 (Box 216, Folder 1)
      - Bee Log, 1951-1962 (Box 216, Folder 2)
      - Burnsville, 1952-1961 (Box 216, Folder 3)
      - Cane River, 1956-1961 (Box 216, Folder 4)
      - Celo, 1957-1958 (Box 216, Folder 5)
      - Day Book,1951, 1955 (Box 216, Folder 6)
      - Green Mountain, 1951-1962 (Box 216, Folder 7)
      - Hamrick, 1951, 1957 (Box 216, Folder 8)
      - Higgins, 1952-1954 (Box 216, Folder 9)
      - Micaville, undated (Box 216, Folder 10)
      - Newdale, 1956-1959 (Box 216, Folder 11)
      - Paint Gap, 1950-1953and undated (Box 216, Folder 12)
      - Pensacola, 1961-1962 (Box 216, Folder 13)
      - Ramsaytown, 1952-1955 (Box 216, Folder 14)
      - Relief, 1955-1956 (Box 216, Folder 15)
      - Sioux, 1950-1955 (Box 216, Folder 16)
      - Swiss, 1954-1956 (Box 216, Folder 17)
      - Toledo, 1951-1952 (Box 216, Folder 18)
      - Vixen, 1952-1953 (Box 216, Folder 19)
      - Windom, 1952-1954 (Box 216, Folder 20)
- Grants Series, 1966-1968
  A small series containing information about government grants, primarily federal, to North Carolina programs mostly in 1967. Included are press releases, correspondence, and telegrams Whitener sent announcing grants that had been approved.
  - Papers, 1966, July-1968, Jan.and undated (Box 217, Folder 1-2)
- Invitations Series, 1956-1968
  In this series are invitations for such functions as conventions, meetings, festivals and celebrations, graduations, receptions,-dedications and openings, special day events, Democratic rallies, anniversary events, dinners, and dances. There also are some invitations for speaking engagements. With an invitation is often a reply or a note as to whether Whitener will accept or decline the invitation. The series illustrates many of the activities of a Congressman's life. The papers are organized in a strictly chronological arrangement.
  - Papers, 1956, Sept. (Box 218, Folder 1)
  - Papers, 1957, Jan.-Dec. (Box 218, Folder 2-6)
  - Papers, 1958, Jan.-Feb. (Box 218, Folder 7)
  - Papers, 1958, Mar.-Dec. (Box 219, Folder 1-3)
  - Papers, 1959, Jan.-Apr. (Box 219, Folder 4-6)
  - Papers, 1959, May-Dec. (Box 220, Folder 1-3)
  - Papers, 1960, Jan.-Feb. (Box 220, Folder 4-5)
  - Papers, 1960, Mar.-Dec. (Box 221, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1961, Jan.-Sept. (Box 222, Folder 1-6)
  - Papers, 1961, Oct.-Dec. (Box 223, Folder 1-2)
  - Papers, 1962, Jan.-Apr. (Box 223, Folder 3-6)
  - Papers, 1962, May-Dec. (Box 224, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1963, Jan.-Apr. (Box 225, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1963, May-Sept. (Box 226, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1963, Oct.-Dec.and undated (Box 227, Folder 1-3)
  - Papers, 1964, Jan.-Mar. (Box 227, Folder 4-6)
  - Papers, 1964, Apr.-Sept. (Box 228, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1964, Oct.-Dec. (Box 229, Folder 1-2)
  - Papers, 1965, Jan.-Aug. (Box 229, Folder 3-5)
  - Papers, 1965, Sept.-Dec. (Box 230, Folder 1-3)
  - Papers, 1965, Feb.-Apr. (Box 230, Folder 4-6)
  - Papers, 1965, May-Dec. (Box 231, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1966, Jan.-Aug. (Box 232, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1966, Sept.-Dec. (Box 233, Folder 1-3)
  - Papers, 1966, Jan.-June (Box 233, Folder 4-6)
  - Papers, 1966, July-Oct. (Box 234, Folder 1-3)
  - Papers, 1967, Jan.-Feb. (Box 234, Folder 4-6)
  - Papers, 1967, Mar.-May (Box 235, Folder 1-5)
  - Papers, 1967, June-Oct. (Box 236, Folder 1-7)
  - Papers, 1967, Nov.-Dec. (Box 237, Folder 1-2)
  - Papers, 1968, Jan.-Mar. (Box 237, Folder 3-5)
  - Papers, 1968, Apr.-Sept. (Box 238, Folder 1-6)
- General Information Series, 1950-1964and undated
  This series contains information on a variety of topics. The subjects have been organized in alphabetical order with a small folder of miscellany at the end. A group of advertisements for office equipment was transferred to the Advertising Collection in the Rubenstein Library. The series contains two major files: Legislative Bills and Subject Files.
  - Legislative Bills
    In the Legislative Bills section there are folders for various House of Representatives Bills, as well as for a Senate bill. Whitener introduced about one half of the House bills represented here. Folders usually contain a copy of the bill, and sometimes printed reports, correspondence, and other background information. Arrangement of the folders is by Congress and session, and by specific bill (H.R.) number. A comprehensive listing of the title and number of each bill in this category is filed in folder one of the first box of the Legislative Bills files.
    - 87th Congress, 1st Session, 1961 (Box 239, Folder 2-4)
    - 87th Congress, 2nd Session, 1962 (Box 239, Folder 5-18)
    - 88th Congress, 1st Session, 1963 (Box 239, Folder 19)
  - Subject Files
    - Agriculture Yearbooks,1957-1958 (Box 239, Folder 20-21)
    - Agriculture Yearbooks,1959-1961 (Box 240, Folder 1-3)
    - Akers Meeting, 1958-1960 (Box 240, Folder 4-6)
      Papers pertaining to an annual stag party given by Whitener, John Akers, and Robert Wren, which was attended by U. S. Congressmen, Senators, and others.
    - Alphabetical Files,1957 (Box 241, Folder 1-23)
      The folders are organized alphabetically by name of correspondent during the 85th Congress, 1st Session. This correspondence with constituents is general in nature concerning such topics as paroles, social security applications, invitations, meetings, foreign aid, bills in Congress, veterans pensions, and the farm program.
    - Alphabetical Files,1958
      Folders of general correspondence, similar to that above, for the 85th Congress, 2nd Session.
      - A-B (Box 241, Folder 24-25)
      - C-Y (Box 242, Folder 1-21)
    - Annual Assay Commission, 1961 (Box 242, Folder 22)
    - Capitol Photographs, undated (Box 242, Folder 23)
    - Census, 1950-1960 (Box 242, Folder 24)
    - Census, 1961 (Box 243, Folder 1)
    - Citizens, Naturalized, 1961-1962Pertains to the Eleventh District. (Box 243, Folder 2)
    - Clerk's Office, 1951-1961and undated (Box 243, Folder 3)
    - Clerks-Employment, 1960-1961 (Box 243, Folder 4)
    - Coble Construction Company, 1959 (Box 243, Folder 5)
    - Committee on the District of Columbia: Monuments Subcommittee, 1961 (Box 243, Folder 6)
    - Committee on Un-American Activities, 1953 (Box 243, Folder 7)
    - Congressional Directory, 1957-1961 (Box 243, Folder 8)
    - Congressional Record, 1957-1962and undated- Consists of correspondence and mailing lists. (Box 243, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence (Duplicates),1957For the recess of the 85th Congress, 1st Session, 1957. (Box 243, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1957-1959 (Box 243, Folder 11)
    - Duke University, 1961 (Box 244, Folder 1)
    - Farmers, 1957 (Box 244, Folder 2)
    - Farmers' Bulletins, 1957-1962 (Box 244, Folder 3-4)
    - Fish Applications, 1957-1961- Requests to the Fish and Wildlife Service for allotments of fish. (Box 244, Folder 5)
    - Foreign Aid Responses, 1960-1962- Constituent reactions by letter to Whitener's speech in Congress on Aug. 17,1961,concerning hisopposition to foreign aid expenditures. (Box 244, Folder 6)
    - Geological Survey, 1950-1957Topographic maps. (Box 244, Folder 7)
    - Gestetner (Duplication), 1959-1962 (Box 244, Folder 8)
    - Health Insurance, 1954-1955 (Box 244, Folder 9)
    - High School Graduates, 1959-1960Lists of names and addresses. (Box 244, Folder 10)
    - High School Groups, 1959-1960- Concerns school classes visiting Washington, D. C. (Box 244, Folder 11)
    - High Schools, 1961- Lists of Seniors (Box 245, Folder 1)
    - Inaugural Parade Tickets, 1960-1961 (Box 245, Folder 2)
    - Inauguration, 1960-1961 (Box 245, Folder 3-4)
    - International Court of Justice and International Criminal Police Organization (INTERPOL),1959 (Box 245, Folder 5)
    - Kennedy, 1960 (Box 245, Folder 6)
    - Kennedy Birthday Celebration, 1961- On Saturday, May 27, 1961, the Democratic National Committee had a fund-raising dinner honoring the President on his birthday. (Box 245, Folder 7)
    - Kennedy Speeches,1962 (Box 245, Folder 8)
    - Legislative Correspondence,1959 (Box 246, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda,1959 (Box 246, Folder 2)
    - Mental Health, 1957 (Box 246, Folder 3)
    - Methodist Missionaries, 1961-1962- Concerns the arrest and detention of four Methodist Missionaries in Angola, Portuguese West African province. (Box 246, Folder 4)
    - Minimum Wage, 1961 (Box 246, Folder 5)
    - National Federation of Independent Business Ballots, 1961-1964- Ballots from polls on various issues, such as imports, income tax, current bills in Congress, labor unions, etc.
      - Papers, 1961-1962 (Box 246, Folder 6-9)
      - Papers, 1962-1963,July (Box 247, Folder 1-5)
      - Papers, 1963, Aug.-1964and undated (Box 248, Folder 1-7)
      - National Historical Wax Museum, 1958-1961 (Box 249, Folder 1)
    - National Symphony Orchestra, 1962 (Box 249, Folder 2)
    - Newcomers, 1958-1961- Lists of newcomers to Gastonia and Gaston County, and letters to them. (Box 249, Folder 3-4)
    - News Releases and Congressional Record Insertions, 1958-1959 (Box 249, Folder 5)
    - Newsletters,1957 (Box 249, Folder 6)
    - Newton, Clint, 1962 (Box 249, Folder 7)
    - North Carolina Congressional Delegation, 1961 (Box 249, Folder 8)
    - North Carolina Tercentenary Commission, 1962-1964and undated (Box 249, Folder 9-10)
    - Passport Forms,1962 (Box 249, Folder 11)
    - Peace Corps, 1961 (Box 249, Folder 12)
    - Photographs, Presidential,1961 (Box 249, Folder 13)
    - The President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity, 1961 (Box 250, Folder 1)
    - Reapportionment,1961 (Box 250, Folder 2-3)
    - Recall Orders, undated (Box 250, Folder 4)
    - Redistricting, 1961 (Box 250, Folder 5)
    - Reese, Thomas, 1962 (Box 250, Folder 6)
    - Robotyped Letters,1950, 1953, 1957-1962and undated (Box 250, Folder 7)
    - Seib, Roswitha, 1962 (Box 250, Folder 8)
    - Space Communications Systems, 1961 (Box 250, Folder 9)
    - Swannanoa Veterans Administration Hospital, 1960 (Box 250, Folder 10)
    - Teen Dem Clubs, 1960-1961 (Box 250, Folder 11)
    - Telegrams, 1962-1966- Copies of telegrams Whitener sent out.
      - Papers, 1962-1963,Aug. (Box 250, Folder 12-13)
      - Papers, 1963, Sept.-1966, Sept. (Box 251, Folder 1-6)
    - Telegraph Account, 1957-1962 (Box 252, Folder 1)
    - Thank you Letters, 1961-1962 (Box 252, Folder 2)
    - Trade Missions, 1961-1962 (Box 252, Folder 3)
    - Upton, Jess, 1962 (Box 252, Folder 4)
    - Veterans, 1957-1959 (Box 252, Folder 5)
    - Visa Application Forms, undated (Box 252, Folder 6)
    - Visually Handicapped, 1961 (Box 252, Folder 7)
    - Yancey County Rural Telephone Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 252, Folder 8)
    - Miscellany, 1957-1964Press releases, clipping, etc. (Box 252, Folder 9)
- Office Files Series, 1951-1968,primarily 1962-1968
  Papers which seem to have been in active use by Whitener's office staff at the time he left office, such as his 1968 correspondence with constituents. In this series are some files that overlap with material in other series, including the Military Academy files and the Military and Veterans files. Three major categories in this series are the District of Columbia, the largest; the the Alphabetical files; and the Voter lists.
  - Alphabetical Files: 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968
    General correspondence on such topics as passport applications, legislation, Social Security disability claims, military and veterans concerns, etc.
    - A-F (Box 253, Folder 1-6)
    - Form Letters-L (Box 254, Folder 1-9)
    - Mc-S (1968, Oct.) (Box 255, Folder 1-8)
    - S (1968, Nov.-Dec.and undated)-Z (Box 256, Folder 1-6)
  - District of Columbia: Committee on the District of Columbia
    Correspondence concerning meetings, hearings on various bills, and referral of bills to Subcommittee No. 4; printed and mimeographed material; and copies of House bills. Letters also refer to bills relative to optometry, bail bond law, establishment of a medical examiner, transportation, and minimum wage.
    - Papers, 1964, Oct.-1965, May (Box 256, Folder 7-9)
    - Papers, 1965, June-1967, Mar. (Box 257, Folder 1-6)
    - Papers, 1967, Apr.-1968, Aug. (Box 258, Folder 1-7)
    - Papers, 1968, Sept.-Oct.and undated (Box 259, Folder 1-2)
  - District of Columbia: General
    Correspondence, telegrams, and printed material, such as clippings and copies of House bills. The papers primarily relate to legislation for the District, relating to such matters as pay for teachers, police, and firemen; gifts to minors; crime and criminal procedure; reorganization of the local government; and a proposed Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority Compact.
    - Papers, 1965-1966,June 22 (Box 259, Folder 3-8)
    - Papers, 1966, June 23-1967, May (Box 260, Folder 1-7)
    - Papers, 1967, June-1968, July 19and undated (Box 261, Folder 1-7)
  - District of Columbia: Subjects
    - Crime Bills, 1965-1967 (Box 262, Folder 1-3)
      In 1965 Whitener introduced H.R. 5688, the Omnibus Crime Bill, and in 1967 he introduced H.R. 1436. Both of these bills related to crime and criminal procedure in the District of Columbia.
    - Home Rule Bills, 1959-1965and undated(primarily1965) (Box 262, Folder 4-5)
    - Housing Bill
      - Papers,1962,Dec; 1963, Mar.-May (Box 262, Folder 6)
      - Papers, 1963, June-1965, Mar.and undated (Box 263, Folder 1-2)
    - Metropolitan Police Department, 1963-1967 (Box 263, Folder 3-5)
    - Omnibus Crime Bill, 1966and undated- Whitener was the author of this bill, H.R. 5688, which President Johnson vetoed. (Box 263, Folder 6)
    - Optometry Act
      - Papers, 1967, Jan. 10-Aug. 14 (Box 263, Folder 7)
      - Papers, 1967, Aug. 14 (Box 264, Folder 1)
    - School Fares, 1957, 1966-1968and undated (Box 264, Folder 2)
    - Transit System
      - Papers,1956, 1962-1966 (Box 264, Folder 3-7)
      - Papers,1967and undated (Box 265, Folder 1-2)
    - Transportation, 1967and undated (Box 265, Folder 3)
    - Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Regulation Compact Amendment, 1966 (Box 265, Folder 4)
  - Military Academies
    This section contains general information about the U.S. military academies. Much material was discarded because it consisted of individual application materials and academic records of the appointees of Whitener and his predecessor, Woodrow W. Jones. These items included correspondence, recommendations, medical records, grade transcripts, biographical data, and academy entrance examination results. The Buckley Amendment of1967to the Privacy Act prohibits the use of such materials without the individual's written consent.
    - Air Force Academy, 1956-1957 (Box 265, Folder 5)
    - Coast Guard Academy, 1951, 1957 (Box 265, Folder 6)
    - Merchant Marine Academy, 1953-1957 (Box 265, Folder 7)
    - Military Academy at West Point, 1965 (Box 265, Folder 8)
    - Naval Academy, 1957 (Box 265, Folder 9)
  - Military and Veterans